Today's דף daf is
דף נ. daf nun. We pick up at the very bottom of
נט עמוד ב. nun tet amud bet. We have moved on beyond
the lung and we have been talking recently
about the קיבה, keivah, a hole
in the fourth stomach of the cow, but it got us into
a discussion about the חלב cheilev on the קיבה, keivah, whether that
fat is forbidden fat or
not and whether חלב cheilev stops up holes. And the גמרא's Gemara
conclusion had been that חלב cheilev that is kosher, which is more
adhesive and sticks to the organs or whatever, stops up holes and
solves טריפה treifa problems, whereas חלב cheilev that is not kosher.
That's right.
Not from kosher animals, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah, the חלב cheilev within the animal that is not
kosher, which the גמרא Gemara describes as two of the criteria. Number
one: it's surrounded by a membrane, and number two: it's sort of
more cloaks over the organ rather than sticks to the organ. And
if you looked at some of these pictures you sort of saw
how some of these organs have like a, almost like a sheath
of חלב cheilev on them. So those are less sticky and therefore
they don't stop up holes.
And this was on the עוף, of, right?
What, the גמרא Gemara doesn't discuss עוף. of. תוספות Tosafot quotes one
of the בעלי תוספות Ba'alei Tosafot who assumed that by the חלב
cheilev of עוף of was sticky and did solve the problem. The
גמרא Gemara doesn't address it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara picks
up.
Okay, we are five lines from the bottom.
אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav Nachman: חלב העשוי ככובא, cheilev ha-asui k'kova,
חלב cheilev that is like a hat, אינו סותם. eino sotem. I'm
sorry, now we're five lines from the bottom, starts with the word
אינו סותם. eino sotem. Does not stop up holes. So that seems
to be the same idea as like a cloak, does not seem
like he's just having a different criteria, just a different description. So
it's sort of like if a hat is a cover on top
of it but does not stick to it, so that again is
the presumably the forbidden fat and also does not stop up holes.
So the
גמרא Gemara says: היכא אמרי ליה היכא, heicha amri lei heicha, where
is this fat that looks like a hat? So אמרי ליה חיטי
דכרכשא ואמרי ליה תרפשא דליבא. amri lei chitey de-karkashah ve-amri lei tirpashah
de-libba. Some say that it is literally the strings, the membranes around
the כרכשא, karkashah, which is the, which is basically the anus and
the large intestine, and some say that it is the membrane around
the heart. Let me see, I think I have a good picture
about the membrane around the heart. You really
see here about how the heart has like this whole little like
cap almost of fat.
And maybe that's מותר muttar חלב, cheilev, right?
That is no, it's forbidden חלב, cheilev, which is why it is
exactly that it does not stop up.
I thought the forbidden... so like here for example is the כרכשא,
karkashah, the large intestine or the rectum, and you see that it's
got like these corpuscles of fat running down them, again that looks
a little bit more like a cloak than a hat but it's
similar to the description in the גמרא. Gemara. And
the כרכשא דליבא, karkashah de-libba, תרפשא דליבא, tirpashah de-libba, oh here.
Okay, so this thing here is a heart, okay? This blue thing
that covers over it, I don't know, it seems to be like
a membrane over the heart, and this is the sort of fat
that's on top of it. So it is sort of like, this
has actually been cut away so that you can see it, it
does not normally expose. Okay, so anyway, this apparently is called the
pericardium is this thing that covers it over, so again it's got
a membrane and it's got this fat around the membrane.
So again you could have described it just like the גמרא Gemara
before with the sheath but here it's being described as a hat.
Okay, yeah, so when we say it's אסור, assur, does that mean
that the two levels of אסור... assur... there's all of it's put
on the
מזבח mizbe'ach or you just can't eat it?
No, not all of it is put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, but
we learn from the fact that it's put on the מזבח mizbe'ach
what are the qualities of חלב cheilev that are forbidden fat. And
they are basically what the גמרא Gemara says: having a membrane and
the debate about whether it's also sheathing the organs that they are
around.
So if it's a קרבן korban and you don't put that part
on the מזבח mizbe'ach and you can't eat it, what do you
do with it?
Throw it out.
Just throw it out. Is that all טריפה?
treifa? Yeah. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so basically it's similar to
what we said before, except here we're describing specifically that it looks
like a hat, which the גמרא Gemara says is true either around
the large intestine or the rectum and the heart.
Yeah, so the lung is damaged. What? Yeah, the lung is damaged,
and that I cannot use, so
the whole
animal is טריפה. treifa. Right. Yep, exactly. That's the whole principle of
this פרק. perek. One injured organ makes the whole animal a טריפה.
treifa.
Yeah. Okay, so אמר רבא: Amar Rava: שמע מינה דרב נחמן תרתי,
sh’ma minah de-Rav Nachman tartei, we hear from רב נחמן Rav Nachman
two things. This idea of רב נחמן Rav Nachman that it's about
whether it's like a hat or not. It's funny the emphasis on
רב נחמן Rav Nachman because it seems to be exactly what we
had been discussing before, but anyway, we infer two things: חימצה ובר
חימצה, chimtza u-bar chimtza, when it comes to the חימצה chimtza and
the בר חימצה, bar chimtza, which are two types of fat which
is on the... קיבה, keiva, so remember we had a whole discussion
before whether the fat on the קיבה keiva was forbidden or not.
Now we're actually going to distinguish between two types of fat on
the קיבה. keiva. So there's something called the חימצא chimtza and the
son of the חימצא, chimtza, חד סתים וחד לא סתים.
chad
satim v'chad lo satim.
One stops up holes and the other does not because apparently one
of them serves more like a hat and the other doesn't. So
it's very funny how it connects this to רב נחמן. Rav Nachman.
There seems to have been exactly this discussion before. Anyway, let's take
a look. ולא ידענא היי מינייהו. v'lo yadana hai minaihu. I don't
know which is which, which is a little bit funny because why
don't you just look and which one is, you know, appears more
like this? And why is it tied to רב נחמן? Rav Nachman?
If it's tied to רב נחמן Rav Nachman because he's describing one
that looks in a certain way, then how could you not know
which is which? So מסקינן maskinan a lot of questions here, I
don't have a lot of answers. Okay, so let's take a look.
רב הונא בר חיננא Rav Huna bar Chinena ורב הונא בריה דרב
נחמן v'Rav Huna brei d'Rav Nachman אמרי amri בר חימצא סתים חימצא
לא סתים. bar chimtza satim, chimtza lo satim. אמר רב טבות, amar
Rav Tavut, וסימנך, v'simonach, the way you can remember this is, יפה
כח הבן מכח האב. yafe koach haben mikoach ha'av. We have a
משנה Mishna in שבועות Shavuot that sometimes a son can take,
can collect a debt that the father would have to make an
שבועה shvua about that he had not been paid. But since there's
no expectation that the son knows whether he's been paid or not,
the son can collect the debt without the שבועה. shvua. So the
line of the משנה Mishna is the son's power is greater than
that of the father. So here what's called the בר חימצא bar
chimtza has more power than the חימצא, chimtza, it's able to be
סתינא. satina. We still don't know which is which, so we're not
done yet.
Isn't the בר bar one the one beneath it, no?
Well, let's take a look. Yes, but beneath it which way?
ריש כסימא דאורייתא. rish kashima d'ora.
All right, so let's take a look. האי חימצא והאי בר חימצא,
hai chimtza v'hai bar chimtza, so finally, okay, so which is which?
Okay, so wonderful. Now you've told us that the בר חימצא סתים.
bar chimtza sotem. I still want to know which is which. So
תא שמע, ta shma, דאמר רב נחמן, d'amar Rav Nachman, once again
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, now this would have made more sense that
it was going on this רב נחמן Rav Nachman because this רב
נחמן Rav Nachman is really talking about the חימצא chimtza rather than
the other רב נחמן Rav Nachman that wasn't talking about it at
all. Anyway, says רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, אינהו מיכל אכלי ולדידן מיסתם
נמי לא סתים. inhu michal achlei v'ladidan mistam nami lo satim.
So here we are about to find out that there was different
practices in בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael they ate this thing called the בר חימצא bar chimtza and
in בבל Bavel they did not. So this is some of the
fat of the קיבה. keiva. We know there's a rabbinic debate about
fat of the קיבה keiva whether it's considered חלב chelev or not.
So in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they considered that it wasn't חלב
chelev and they ate it. If they ate it, we know fat
that you eat is considered to be what? סתים. sotem. Okay. In
בבל Bavel they had a practice not to eat it. So the
question is, is their practice not to eat it because they weren't
exactly sure, it was a חומרא, chumra, or did they really פסקן
pasken it was forbidden fat? So there's actually a debate of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות Tosafot how you read this line in the גמרא.
Gemara. תוספות Tosafot reads it as a simple declarative statement. They eat
from the fat, in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they eat from this
בר חימצא, bar chimtza, but for us we don't eat from it,
ולדידן מיסתם נמי לא סתים, v'ladidan mistam nami lo satim, it doesn't
still close up.
And why is that strange?
No, I mean, if it close or not close, I mean just
eat, you know, fat from the other close or wouldn't and just
do your experiment.
No, because we know that it fills the hole. The question in
all these things is, does it fill it well enough? Also a
membrane covers the hole. The question in all these things is, does
it do it well enough that we say that it stops the
animal from being a טריפה, treifa, that it's going to be permanent?
Okay, so the way תוספות Tosafot reads this is, what is the
בר חימצא bar chimtza that we're discussing? So the בר חימצא bar
chimtza we're discussing is this fat on the קיבה keiva that is
the debate between ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל. Bavel. So for
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they eat it and for them of course
it would be סתים. sotem. For us, we don't eat it and
it's not סתים. sotem. That's the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. But
it's a little funny. Could have said they eat it, we don't
eat it. You know, what's they eat it and for us it's
not סתים? sotem? So רש"י Rashi reads this word בתמיה. bitmiya. רש"י
Rashi reads this as, look, they in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael will
even go so far to eat the בר חימצא. bar chimtza. We,
okay, we don't eat it. That's our חומרא, chumra, that's our מנהג.
minhag. But we're not going to say that it doesn't have the
properties of being adhesive and being סתים, sotem, you know? And actually
points to the fact that maybe these two categories are not always
exactly coincide. Maybe something could be forbidden fat and still have more
adhesive qualities, or at least the way רש"י Rashi says is, you
know, maybe it's a חומרא chumra we don't eat, maybe because it's
a מחלוקת. machlokes. Remember there was a מחלוקת machlokes before what defines
forbidden fat we don't eat. But we'll certainly acknowledge that it has
the ability to be סתים. sotem. So that's the way רש"י Rashi
reads it. So what is this fat, this בר חימצא bar chimtza
that's סתים? sotem? The thing that is eaten in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael. And even though it's not eaten in בבל Bavel it still
will be סתים. sotem. Now what is it? Okay, so still describe
to me what is it? So the גמרא Gemara is finally going
to get to that. Let's take a look. Top of נ' עמוד
א'. nun amud aleph. Okay, דאקשתא כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסירא, d'akashta
kuli alma lo pligi d'asira, but the stuff that is on the
bow, קשת, keshet, everybody agrees is forbidden. Basically the קיבה, keiva, you
can look at the picture but let me just describe it. The
קיבה keiva looks like a, you know, sort of like a crescent
or croissant if you will. So there's the outer bow which is
called the קשת, keshet, the אקשתא, akashta, right, and then there's the
inner part which is called the יתרה yatera which I think comes
from the fact that that's where you would, if it was a
bow, that's where you would string the string.
יתרה דכבדא, yatera d'akaved, is that what you mean?
No, no, not יתרה, yatera, יתרה, yatera, but it does mean like
I think it means. but I think it means because
of להתיר L'Hatiyer and I'm not sure, I didn't look up the
etymology, but I think it comes from the word to string. Anyway,
there's the outer part of the crescent and the inner part of
the crescent. Okay, so the outer apparently the fat there has different
qualities and it's more classically forbidden fat than the inner part of
the crescent. Okay, so the outer's called the חמצה Chimtsa and the
inner is the בר חמצה Bar Chimtsa because it's the smaller crescent.
Okay, so that's what we're about to say. דקשתא Dakashta on the
bow, the outer bow, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דאסיר, Kulei alma lo
pligi d'Asir, everybody agrees that fat is forbidden fat and it's forbidden
and therefore it's not סותם. Sotem. כי פליגי, Ki pligi, where's this
debate between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל? Eretz Yisrael? דאיתרא D'Ayitara on
the inner crescent. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'Amri, some say that and the
inner crescent so that's the בר חמצה, Bar Chimtsa, they eat it
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, they don't eat it in בבל, Bavel,
but the argument is even if they don't eat it, the way
רש"י Rashi reads, at least it will be סותם. Sotem. איכא דאמרי,
Ika d'Amri, some say that it's even more strict, דאיתרא כולי עלמא
לא
פליגי דשרי, D'Ayitara kulei alma lo pligi d'shari, more lenient.
The inner crescent everybody agrees is permissible, which again makes it good,
that's the בר חמצה, Bar Chimtsa, everybody agrees it's permissible fat and
therefore everybody agrees that it is סותם, Sotem, which is what we
said before, the בר חמצה Bar Chimtsa is סותם. Sotem. כי פליגי
דאקשתא, Ki pligi d'akashta,
when do they debate the outer crescent? That there in ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael they even eat the outer crescent, they don't eat it
in בבל, Bavel, and if they don't eat it in בבל, Bavel,
that's presumably why that wouldn't be סותם, Sotem, but at least the
inner crescent is. So what we know is the inner crescent is
better, it could be that they even will eat that in...
it could be that everybody agrees that that's permissible fat, at least
at most, at most it's debated whether that's permissible fat and therefore
the inner crescent will definitely be סותם. Sotem. Okay, so now let's
see, כי הא דאמר רב אוויא אמר רב אמי Ki ha d'Amar
Rav Avya Amar Rav Ami מקמצן. Mikamtsan.
That like that which רב אוויא Rav Avya says in the name
of רב אמי, Rav Ami, you pull it off, which what means
what or you tear... you take off a layer, which means that
apparently this fat lies right next to actual forbidden fat from the
other organs, so if you're going to eat this fat you have
to peel off like, you know, take off a thin layer because
of or it mixes with the really forbidden fat and then you
can go ahead and eat it. Okay, so therefore you see that
they actually, once they took off a thin layer of to get
rid of the forbidden fats from the other organs, they would go
ahead and eat it. Okay,
רש"י Rashi says because it would be the חלב Chelev of the
כרת. Karet. Now it's not exactly clear one minute whether they're talking
about the outer crescent or the inner, but presumably the outer, just
because that is... this is being brought to support that there was
those that, you know, that there's a possible read that even the
outer crescent is okay. So let's take a look at a few
more examples of this. וכן אמר רב ינאי משום חד זקן, V'chein
Amar Rav Yannai mishum chad zakein, similarly said רב ינאי Rav Yannai
מקמצן, Mikamtsan, you like, you know, peel it off and you eat
it. אמר רב אוויא Amar Rav Avya הוינא קמיה דרב אמי, Havina
kamei d'Rav Ami, I was in front of רב אמי Rav Ami
וקמצו והבו ליה, V'kamtsu v'havu leh,
they peeled off the, you know, a layer of it and then
they gave him the rest of the fat to eat, ואכל, v'achal,
and he ate it. שמעיה דרבי חנינא Shmaya d'Rabbi Chanina הוה קאי
קמיה דרבי חנינא, hava ka'i kamei d'Rabbi Chanina, the servant of רבי
חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, the assistant was in front of רבי חנינא, Rabbi
Chanina, אמר ליה Amar leh קמוץ הב לי דאיכול, Kmuts hav li
d'eichol, so רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina said to him, "Go peel off
for me a layer of the fat so I could eat the
rest." He wanted to eat this חלב Chelev which was on the
קיבה. Keivah. חזייה דהוה קמחסם, Chazya d'hava kamchasam,
he saw that he was hesitating. אמר ליה, Amar leh, so רבי
חנינא Rabbi Chanina said to his assistant, "בבלאת! Bavlat! What, you're a
Babylonian? And you don't eat from this fat and therefore you don't
want to give it to me to eat from it? קום שדי!
Kum shadi! Go ahead, chop it off and just, you know, throw
it all out." If you don't... which is very considerate of him.
He could have said, "You're my servant, what do I care if
you eat it or not?" But he says, "Oh, okay, I didn't
realize you were so sensitive to it, you think that this is
טרייף, Treif, fine, throw it all off, cut it off and throw
it out." Okay, so here you see this difference between בבל... Bavel...
what?
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael.
רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina was from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. All these
were from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. So here you see again that
they ate it in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Again, it's not so
clear from the examples whether they're talking about the outer crescent or
the inner crescent, but clearly the fat on the inner... on the
inner crescent
was... you know, more agreed, possibly even in בבל Bavel that it
was permissible and that's the בר חמצה Bar Chimtsa that at least
is what is סותם. Sotem. Yes, Michael, you had a question.
Just if you're able to do this, can you just break down
for me which are the ones that are on the מזבח, Mizbeach,
which are the ones forbidden, which are the ones that are מותר?
Mutar?
Not exactly, because off the top of my head, but I will
say I mean what the תורה Torah emphasizes is כל חלב על
הקרב ואת כל החלב אשר על הקרב. Kol chelev al hakerev v'et
kol hachelev asher al hakerev. There's one,
there's a nice picture here in Situ 2, Situ 2, Situ 2.
Anyway, all of this wonderful yellow, right, which is all filling up
all of the cavity, so this is the חלב על הקרב, Chelev
al hakerev, right, and the...
הקרב hakerev is like here, like the inner intestines, and this is
חלב המכסה את הקרב ואת כל החלב אשר על הקרב. Chelev hamichaseh
et hakerev v'et kol hachelev asher al hakerev.
So this basically all of these big, you know, huge amounts of
fats that are filling up the stomach of it. Okay, and the
גמרא Gemara describes...
these are the ones on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Yeah.
And the גמרא Gemara describes that as again, stuff that's encased in
a membrane and that more like sheaths or lays on top of
the organs, as opposed to stuff, if you think about the fat,
although that might be שומן shuman already. Again, I don't know enough
that I can describe this accurately. There's stuff which is, you know,
which is actually שומן, shuman, which is not even called fat, as
opposed to here the word's saying it's חלב chelev but it's not
forbidden enough. Right, but there's stuff which is actually by consistency clearly
different. Okay, the stuff that's like embedded in your steak, that's not
חלב, chelev, that's שומן, shuman, you know, that's stuff like in between
the meat. This is stuff that's actually on top some people get
something from the butcher, oh it's חלב, chelev, they're always, completely, completely.
All this stuff is on top of the organs, but again, if
it's sticky and adhesive and not in a membrane, then it's more
the permissible stuff.
That's מזבח, mizbeach, none of the forbidden stuff is...
is anything that has that consistency, that basically is encased in a
membrane and is... what?
I'm more interested in location.
Well, yeah, well, so, okay, so we're talking about stuff that's on
the small intestines and on the, I mean, you know, on the
heart, on all these places. I mean, I don't know, every stuff
that has... I can't tell you. Okay, anyway, here you see is
some... here, this is a חלב המכסה את הקרב, chelev hamachase et
hakerev, okay?
Anyway,
but to the next... what?
That's the stuff that goes on the מזבח. mizbeach. All right, anyway,
let's continue. Yeah, let me just see if I can show you,
here, here this is a nice example about the consistency. Here it
is קרום ונקלף, krum veniklaf, right? It's got like this membrane around
it, it totally is sheathing here the kidneys, it's like totally surrounding
an organ and it's got like a membrane on it. Okay?
So yeah, so רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, if I understand this right,
he was asking his servant to give him...
רבי חנינא... Rabbi Chanina... right, and the servant was hesitating. Right, let's
say some... why did he...
I mean, why... well, like he was asking the servant to eat.
I understand. It just shows how nice and sensitive he was. He
didn't want the servant to feel that he was being מכשיל machshil
him or just... you know, just to maybe even a taboo response.
Oh, maybe it was just that nice: Oh, I didn't realize you
were a Babylonian, I would have never asked you or done something
like that to offend. Anyway, here is what it looks like. Here
you see,
here's the cre... I have no idea how they ate it. Yeah,
it sounds like maybe as a butter substitute or something. שמאלץ? shmalz?
Anyway, here's the crescent look of this thing. Okay? Anyway, all right,
let's keep on going.
So that's the חלב, chelev, that was the forbidden fat?
Yeah, the one with the membrane. All right, let's continue. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא, Tanya, we taught in a ברייתא:
Baraita: רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer: בני
מעיים שניקבו. benei mei'in shenikvu.
Now we are moving away from fat, and we go back to
holes in organs. Okay, so if you have some of the inner
organs that got a hole in them, until now we've been talking
about membranes, which are no good for permissible fat, חלב, chelev, which
is good. Now we're going to talk about that their own mucus
comes to fill the hole. Is that considered a good filling of
the hole? So let's take a look. בני מעיים שניקבו, benei mei'in
shenikvu, if these inner organs got a hole in them, ולחה סותמן,
velecha sotman, and some type of a, you know, mucus fills them,
כשרה, keshera, it's כשר. kasher. מאי לחה, mai lecha, what type of
mucus are we talking about? So אמר רב כהנא: Amar Rav Kahana:
שירקא דמיעיא דנפיק אגב דוחקא. shirkeda demei'aya denafik agav duchka. Again,
the mucus of the organs that comes out through pressure, so some
type of mucus from the very, you know, skin itself that comes
to, from the organ itself, that comes to fill the hole. גמירי
חברייא דרבי אבא מרבי אבא. Gemiri chavraya deRabbi Abba miRabbi Abba. So
the colleagues of רבי אבא Rabbi Abba learn from רבי אבא. Rabbi
Abba. ומאן הוא, uman hu, who was the colleague? רבי זירא. Rabbi
Zeira. Okay, so רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira learned from רבי אבא. Rabbi
Abba. ואמרי לה, ve'amrei lah, and some say the reverse: חברייא דרבי
זירא מרבי זירא. chavraya deRabbi Zeira miRabbi Zeira. The colleague of רבי
זירא Rabbi Zeira learned from רבי זירא. Rabbi Zeira. ומאן הוא, uman
hu, רבי אבא, Rabbi Abba, and it was רבי אבא. Rabbi Abba.
So we know that רבי אבא Rabbi Abba and רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira were colleagues, and one of them learned from the other the
following teaching. So אמר רבי אבא, Amar Rabbi Abba, some have that
גירסא girsa but רש"י Rashi points out it's not the same רבי
אבא, Rabbi Abba, it would be quite bizarre. בריה דרבי חייא בר
אבא, brei deRabbi Chiya bar Abba, the son of רבי חייא בר
אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, so he's named after his grandfather. הכי
אמר רבי חייא בר אבא, hachi amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, again,
interesting if you read it with the parentheses, here's what my father
said, a lot of אבא, Abba, a lot of אבא Abba's going
on here. Anyway, here's what רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba my father says: אמר רבי יוחנן: Amar Rabbi Yochanan: הלכה כרבן
שמעון בן גמליאל בטריפה, halacha keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel betreifa,
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel by
טריפה, treifa, והלכה כרבי שמעון באבל. vehalacha keRabbi Shimon ba'avel. And we
rule like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by אבל. avel. הלכה כרבן שמעון
בן גמליאל בטריפה הא דאמרן, halacha keRabban Shimon ben Gamliel betreifa hadaman,
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel by
טריפה treifa regarding what we just said, that the mucus from the
organ itself is a good filler of the hole. Okay, so remember,
this is a big challenge, right? What would be sufficient filler of
the hole? So one again, we said that a simple membrane, which
you would think would be the most obvious, is not because we
think it will tear. We have spoken about when it's, you know,
against other organs and there's other types of either naturally that closes
it up or adhesions that keep them together, those are ways of
closing it. We've mentioned חלב, chelev, and now we're talking about its
own type of mucus that comes to or, you know, pus and
not pus, whatever, anyway, mucus that comes to fill it. So he
says we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel
that that does fill a hole.
And כרבי שמעון באבל, keRabbi Shimon ba'avel, like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
when it comes to אבלות, avelus, מאי? mai? So now a totally
unrelated topic. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה: Mishnah: כל שלושה
ימים הראשונים, kol shelosha yamim harishonim, כל מי מקום קרוב מונה עמהן,
kol mi makom karov moneh imahen, מי מקום. mi makom. מונה לעצמו.
moneh le-atzmo. For the first three days, if this person, he's a
member of the household, somebody died, the father died let's say, and
one of the brothers lives in a nearby town, מקום קרוב makom
karov as they said within a day's journey, and he was not
aware that the father had died and he shows up, the father
had died on Sunday, and he shows up on Monday, on Tuesday.
So the concept is, you know, which is actually a very powerful
concept which we still פוסקן pasken but sometimes we lose a little
sight of, that the idea that almost the idea that the household
is in אבלות, avelus, not just as individuals. There's a whole concept
of a גדול הבית gadol ha-bayis determining when אבלות avelus begins and
so on. So here, this guy showed up on Tuesday. Everybody's been
sitting since Sunday. Okay? But because he is part of a member
of the household and he was in a מקום קרוב makom karov
where he could have heard within time, which is considered within a
day's journey, it's as if virtually as if he did hear and
is as if he's part of that household and therefore if he
comes within the first three days,
he
joins the household, thank you, I was looking for a word for
משתתף, mishtatef, anyway he joins the household and his אבלות avelus goes,
starts from Sunday even though he personally did not start sitting שבעה
shiva until Tuesday. Okay, anytime within three days, we'll talk about these
specifics anyway, anytime within three days, בא ממקום קרוב מונה עמהם ba
mi-makom karov moneh im-mahem if he comes from a nearby place he
counts with them, ממקום רחוק מונה לעצמו mi-makom rachok moneh le-atzmo because
then even though he showed up he was never considered to be
conceptually part of that same household even if he came within the
first three days. But he was always seen as, you know, you
moved away to California. I didn't realize you were going to happen
to be visiting in New York. But once you're living in California
you're no longer conceptually, you know, part of the same שבעה. shiva.
Okay, so that's even in the three days. מכאן ואילך mi-kan va-eilach
after the first three days,
אפילו בא ממקום קרוב מונה לעצמו afilu ba mi-makom karov moneh le-atzmo
he counts שבעה shiva on his own counting based on when he
finds out. רבי שמעון אומר אפילו ביום השביעי Rabbi Shimon omer afilu
be-yom ha-shevi'i even up till the seventh day, בא ממקום קרוב מונה
עמהם ba mi-makom karov moneh im-mahem if he's from a nearby place
even if he shows up on the very last day,
he combines with them and is considered to have sat שבעה shiva
together with them and only counts until their שבעה shiva is done.
תוספות Tosafos raises the question: what do you mean on the seventh
day? On the seventh day they already got up in the morning.
So תוספות Tosafos says before they got up, right, if they're still
mourners, consolers there, you know, paying a שבעה shiva call, the שבעה
shiva doesn't end until the consolers leave. So as long as he
showed up before the consolers leave, he counts with them. So now
we are saying we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel that this is true even until the seventh day. So,
אמר מן דהוא, amar man d'hu, a certain person said, very interesting,
מן דהוא, man d'hu, somebody, we don't know, רש״י Rashi said that
the
בעלי הגמרא ba'alei ha-gemara knew this story but they forgot who it
was told in the name of. So you don't get that too
often. אמר מן דהוא, amar man d'hu, what's-his-name said, that's how I
talk about someone, what's-his-name said, איסק ואיסיק וגמר שמעתתא מפומיה דמרה. iski
v'eisik v'gamru shema'sei mi-pumei d'mara.
I should merit and go up to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
learn this teaching from the one who taught it. Remember this is
again a fascinating repeat recurring theme that we've been having about going
and checking out the מסורה mesorah and finding out whether the מסורה
mesorah is accurate or not. So a certain person once again like
we learned yesterday said 'I'm going to go and find out, I
want to hear this straight from the horse's mouth what we really
said about this.' Okay, so let's take a
look. כי סליק ki salik when he went up to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, אשכחיה לרבי אבא בריה דרבי חייא, ashkechei le-Rabbi Abba breih
de-Rabbi Chiya, he found Rabbi Abba the son of Rabbi Chiya, remember
that was the one who it was said in the name of,
in the name of רבי יוחנן בר אבא, Rabbi Yochanan bar Abba,
the son of Abba, I'm sorry did I split? No, רבי אבא
בריה דרבי חייא בר אבא. Rabbi Abba breih de-Rabbi Chiya bar Abba.
אמר ליה אמר מר הלכה כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל בטריפה? amar lei
amar mar halachah ke-Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel bi-treifah? Did you actually say
we rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel by
טריפה, treifah, by this mucus that stops the hole? What do you
think he's going to say? אמר ליה הא אין הלכה אמרי. amar
lei ha ein halachah amri. No,
I said we don't rule like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel by טריפה. treifah. אוי וי, oy vey, so it's very
fascinating again how much in you can really see why this is
learned for people who get סמיכה semichah because it's even though טריפות
treifos is now like a specialized thing but how much about the
sort of process of פוסקן, paskening, you know, that are coming up
here how much real cases are being dealt with and you know
this whole idea about checking out מסורה mesorah two days within two
דפים. dapim. Okay, I said the הלכה halachah is not like רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel בטריפה. bi-treifah. כרבי שמעון באבלות
מאי? ke-Rabbi Shimon ba-avelus mai?
So he says 'okay, now that we got that cleared up, what's
your position about ruling like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when it comes
to the אבלות avelus question?' So אמר ליה פלוגתא נינהו. amar lei
pelugta ninhu. That's a debate. דאתמר de-itmar it was said: רב חסדא
אמר הלכה, Rav Chisda amar halachah, we rule like רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, וכן אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה. ve-khen amar Rabbi Yochanan halachah.
Now that actually he we did say before, right, because before it
said it was in the name of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But
here we're saying that maybe he himself did not feel that that
was a definitive פסק, psak, because when asked what the פסק psak
is he says okay רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we rule like
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, ורב נחמן אמר אין הלכה, ve-Rav Nachman amar
ein halachah, we don't rule like him. And now the גמרא Gemara
concludes like the גמרא Gemara concluded yesterday after showing different versions of
the tradition,
ואין הלכה כרבי שמעון. ve-ein halachah ke-Rabbi Shimon. But we do
rule, but it says והלכה כרבי שמעון באבל. ve-halacha k'Reb Shimon be-avel.
We do rule like רב שמעון Reb Shimon by אבל avel that
if somebody comes even on the seventh day, he's משתתף, mishtatef, he
combines with them for the שבעה, shiva, דאמר שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, as
Chazal says, הלכה כדברי המקל באבל. halacha ke-divrei ha-mekil be-avel.
We always rule like the more lenient position when it comes to
issues of אבילות. aveilus. So there you go, as far as we're
concerned, excuse me, the טריפה treifa issue, we do not rule that
this mucus fills up holes, but as far as the אבילות aveilus
issue, we rule that even if the גדול הבית, gadol habayit, even
if somebody shows up on day seven, he's מונה עמהם. moneh imahem.
It's like רב אשי. Rav Ashi. Who exactly was the מסדר גמרא
mesader gemara is a question, but this is the ש"ס, shas, the
בת, bas, the סתם stam of the גמרא, gemara, whoever wrote the
anonymous voice of the גמרא, gemara, in the end the גמרא's gemara
concluding that way. So again quite fascinating about different versions of what
the actual מסורה mesorah was.
Regarding אבילות, aveilus, is that basically moot because you can get anywhere
in a day?
That's an interesting question how exactly we פוסקן pasken about
that.
But let's say somebody's it can happen, it's nothing to do with
his parents anymore, they lost touch, moved far away, has a brother,
then people come, then people regret it.
Where do we פוסקן pasken it? What we actually say למעשה le-ma'aseh
is an interesting question.
I don't remember ever how I mean issues about שמועה קרובה, shmu'ah
kerovah, שמועה רחוקה shmu'ah rechokah you get. I don't remember offhand when
ever we פוסקן pasken this case.
I have to I would have to look it up.
First of all, the שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch defines מקום קרוב mekom
karov both in terms of geographic distance and יבוא ביום אחד, yavo
be-yom echad, שמהלך י' פרסאות שאפשר שיבוא
ביום אחד. she-mahalach yud parsos she-efshar she-yavo be-yom echad. So מהלך, mahalach,
if you go by מהלך י' פרסאות, mahalach yud parsos, which I
imagine we would, then that would be what is that? That's pretty
close, that's
what, four five miles, something like that?
I mean so someone in New Jersey, if the parent's in New
York, it's kind of hard to say, it's a twenty minute drive
but it's not more than ten י' פרסאות. yud parsos.
So
technically we פוסקן pasken it, but how we actually פוסקן pasken it,
and again given that we probably do not define יום אחד, yom
echad, we probably emphasize more the geographic distance than the actual יום
אחד, yom echad, it's hard for cases like this to really happen
so much because we're talking about within a few miles.
I can try to get back to you on that.
Alright, let's
turn to, time it would take for him to walk vs the
amount of
time for the message to get to him at a certain time.
No, י' פרסאות yud parsos is normally the amount of time we
assume it takes to walk in a day. The גמרא gemara uses
that in
גמרא פסחים gemara pesachim on דף, daf, like כמה הוא מהלך אדם
בינוני ביום.
kama hu mahalach adam
benoni be-yom. It's י' פרסאות yud parsos and so on.
What? 1.5
miles in a day?
That's true.
That is true. Okay, yeah. I'll have to get back to you
on all of that. Let's go on. Okay. אמר רב שימי בר
חייא מקיפין בפני מעיים. Amar Rav Shimi bar Chiya: Makifin bifnei me'ayim.
Now
this had come up before. Once again we have the interesting thing,
on the one hand we have all these stringencies we've told, but
now you have this question about ways to say maybe the hole
didn't come now, maybe it came after שחיטה. shechita. Yesterday we talked
about the place where the שוחט shochet handles it, can we assume
that that actually created a hole? Now we're talking about that it
wasn't where the שוחט shochet handles it, you see a hole, but
you for some reason either there's a reason to suspect it came
after שחיטה shechita or just סתם stam you would like to believe
it came after שחיטה. shechita. The way you can test actually is
what you do is you take another place within the same organ,
you actually make a hole, and you look and you compare them.
And if they look similar, then you assume that it came after
שחיטה shechita because there would be a different look to it if
the hole was made after שחיטה shechita or the hole was made
during שחיטה. shechita. So that's a big קולא, kula, on the one
hand you have all these things about סרכות sirchas whatever, all these
worries about holes etc, and here you say, I see a hole,
but you do a little type of an experiment and you can
use that to assume that the hole came after
שחיטה. shechita. מקיפין, makifin, now מקיפין makifin means like להקיף le-hakif is
to put together, to surround, but it means that you lay them
next to each other and you compare, you do a side-by-side comparison.
So you מקיפין בפני מעיים, makifin bifnei me'ayim, you're allowed to do
that to make a hole and to compare them. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara says: הנהו בני מעייא דאתו לקמיה דרבא. Hanu benei
me'ayim de-asu lekamei de-Rava. So there were certain types of inner organs
that came to רבא.
Rava. A long time ago, which is not, talking about רבא. Rava.
We're going to talk about the רבא. Rava. אקפינהו, akfinhu, he compared
them, he made a hole obviously in a different place and looked
at it side-by-side. and it wasn't similar. So he said, sorry, you
have to assume it came when the animal was alive. So אתא
רב משרשיא בריה, ata Rav Marshorshie brei, so Rav Marshorshie's son came,
ממשמש בהו, mimashmesh bahu, he took with the new hole was made
and he rubbed it a little bit, he handled it with his
hands, ודמי, v'idmi, and now it looks just like the other hole.
So, so אמר ליה, amar lei, מנלך הא? menalach ha? So he
said, look, you see basically it is, it does look the same.
The only thing was, the other one looked different because it had
been handled already. This, you just made was a fresh hole, it
hadn't been handled. Once you handle it, it looks the same and
we can assume it came after שחיטה. shechita. So אמר, amar, so
Rava said to him, מנלך הא, menalach ha, where did you get
this idea? So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back to Rava,
his father, his son: כמה ידי ממשמשו בהני מיקמי דלייתו לקמיה דמר.
kama yadei mimashmeshu behani mikami d'leito l'kamei d'mar. How many hands must
have handled this organ before it was presented to you? So obviously
this thing is being handled a lot. So I figured maybe that
affected what the hole looked like. So I made a hole, so
you made a hole, so I handled it and we'll see if
it looks the same. So basically I figured it out on my
own.
אמר ליה, amar lei, so Rava said to him, חכים ברי בטרפות
כרבי יוחנן. chakim brei b'treifos k'Rabbi Yochanan. My son and his brilliance.
We had this line before you might remember, when it comes to
טרפות treifos as Rabbi Yochanan. Rashi says either as Rabbi Yochanan is
in general, like a saying like he's as brilliant as Einstein, or
particularly Rabbi Yochanan was known to be an expert in טרפות. treifos.
So wow, that was brilliant. So they were able to מתיר matir
it based on that. Okay, so again, pretty amazing. All these worries
about holes, but now you do a little test and you can
assume somehow the hole came afterwards.
Okay, רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Elazar d'amri
tarvaihu, now Rabbi Yochanan himself and Rabbi Elazar says, מקיפין בריאה, makifin
b'reia, even when it comes to the lungs. So yesterday we said
if it's a place where the שוחט shochet normally handles it, then
you can assume that it came from the שוחט, shochet, which was
pretty amazing, assuming that there are ways in which it looks like
a type of a thing that would be made by the handling
of a שוחט. shochet. Rashi says here, even if it's in a
place where you wouldn't normally assume the שוחט shochet handled it, you
could still do this test. And if it looked similar, the hole,
the new hole that you made to the hole that was first,
you would assume that it was an after שחיטה shechita hole.
Somehow it just got there.
Yeah, well, not somehow, there's a lot of knives flying around. That's
the whole point, that presumably a hole made by a knife is
going to look different than a type of a naturally formed hole.
Although you do wonder since we've been talking before about holes made
by needles, what if you made this new hole by a needle?
How different would it really look? So again, I find this quite
fascinating that these things are sufficient. It's almost like when we know
exactly what happened, we can have a principle that like membranes don't
seal up holes, even though to us it would seem like why
not? Or even a סירכא sircha means that we know a hole
was there. If those are our principles, those are our principles. But
if we actually, there's some doubt as to whether this actually was
a hole when the animal was alive, we more go by this
idea of חזקת כשרות chezkat kashrut and we're more willing to attribute
it to other sources if we have a reasonable way to attribute
it to other sources.
But you have to have a doubt. Well, that's not clear. It
sounds from this גמרא Gemara that any hole you can,
I mean I guess if it's clear from the way it looks
that it was מחיים, me'chayim, you have to assume מחיים. me'chayim. But
the basic way the גמרא Gemara sounds like any hole you can
do this test. And if it looks similar to a hole that
you've now just made as the animal is alive, that's a way
to say that it's not a problem. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara goes on, אמר רבא לא אמרו אלא באותה ארוגה. amar Rava
lo amru ela b'osah arugah. When can we compare a hole in
the ריאה? reia? When it's a hole made in that same line,
like of the same sort of surface, like the edge or the
front or whatever. אבל מארוגה לארוגה לא. aval me'arugah l'arugah lo.
You cannot make a hole in a different area of the lung
and compare it to like from one row to another row. והלכתא,
v'hilchata, but the law is אפילו מארוגה לארוגה, afilu me'arugah l'arugah, even
from one row to another row. מדקה לדקה ומגסה לגסה, midaka l'daka
u'migasa l'gasa,
and you can also compare if you're doing different organs. Let's take
not just within the same organ make a hole and compare it.
Let's take a different lung, make a hole in it and look
at the hole in this lung. So you can compare from small
animals like sheep and goats to sheep and goats, or from cows
to cows.
Oh, does it mean like I'd make a hole in this new
sheep and goat?
It does, it could mean that. Okay. And so until now we've
been assuming you have one organ and you make a new hole
and you compare it to the existing hole. Now we're saying that
you use a good organ from another animal and you make the
hole and you compare it. So you can do that, אבל לא
מגסה לדקה ולא מדקה לגסה, aval lo migasa l'daka v'lo midaka l'gasa,
but you cannot compare the, make a new hole in a sheep
or goat's organ and compare it to a cow or vice-versa. Okay,
so now we have another big way that if you have a
hole, maybe you can't stop it up, but maybe you have a
way of saying that it came after שחיטה. shechita. אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרווייהו, Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarvaihu, Abaye and Rava both say, מקיפין בקנה.
makifin b'kaneh. You can also do this test, this comparison when it
comes to the, the trachea. Now this is bizarre because remember a
trachea is only a problem if the majority of it is cut
through. So, I mean, you could certainly imagine that that could happen
after שחיטה, shechita, you have a knife, you're cutting things and accidentally
you cut through the trachea, but it's a little bit hard to
compare two areas where you have a major cut through unless again
you take another trachea and you make the
cut through. so there you can imagine that you could compare two
places in the same trachea with that problem that you can do
similar comparisons with the trachea. אמר פפא לא אמרן אלא באותו חוליה
Amar Pappa lo amran ela be'oto chulya that only within that section
of the rings, right, trachea has all of these cartilage all these
rings, so only within a particular ring section. אבל מחוליה לחוליה Aval
mechulya lechulya from one ring section to another ring section, לא, lo,
then it's not a legitimate comparison. והלכתא Vehilchata but the law is
אפילו מחוליה לחוליה afillu mechulya lechulya even from one ring section to
another, ומבר חוליה לבר חוליה umibar chulya levar chulya
from the son of the ring to the son of the ring.
What's the בר חוליה? bar chulya? So רש"י Rashi basically says it's
either the sort of soft skin between the cartilage, between the rings,
I see you have a gorgeous picture there, or even the cartilage
around, the ring around, when it gets to it's not like a
hundred percent the hard cartilage, when it gets to like the back
twenty percent, it's actually softer material, so that might be the בר
חוליה. bar chulya. Okay, so you cannot compare a hole in the
harder cartilage to a hole in the softer skin. אבל Aval
but you can compare cartilage to cartilage and softer skin to softer
skin, אבל לא מחוליה לבר חוליה ולא מבר חוליה לחוליה aval lo
mechulya levar chulya velo mibar chulya lechulya but not from the soft
to the cartilage or vice versa. Okay, so that's all a very
big קולא. kula. Okay, yes, you can't, maybe not so many things
stop up holes, but you can have ways to save the whole
thing after שחיטה. shechita. אמר זעירי. Amar Zeiri. Now זעירי Zeiri says
חלחולת שנקבה, Chacholet shenikva,
this is the rectum or the large intestine that got a hole
in it, כשרה, kesheira, that actually is not a problem because you
know the משנה Mishnah did not mention all of the inner organs,
so he's saying if it's the חלחולת chacholet it's כשרה. kesheira. Let
me see if we have a picture of it in situ here.
It's pretty big.
Not seeing it here. Maybe on the other side?
Yeah, okay, there you go.
Okay, here's the actual anus you can see right where stuff is
coming out and here is the חלחולת chacholet which is the, I
think it's large intestine. Okay, so it's basically where all of the
waste matter is going through. Okay, now you see it's right at
the back and it's right basically by the thighs of the animal.
Okay, so that was not mentioned in the משנה Mishnah at all.
So he says if that has a hole in it, כשרה kesheira
it's kosher, הואיל וירכיים מעמידות אותה, hoil veyerechayim ma'amidot otah,
since the thighs of the animal keep it in its place, and
you know as רש"י Rashi sort of says the likelihood that
actual waste matter would actually come out of there
when it's already there and it's the hard dry matter is very
unlikely, so therefore it's not really a טריפה treifa by the way
the animal's formed and the type of things that go through it.
Let's see thing here just, this חלחולת, chacholet, they're saying it's the
rectum.
The rectum, not the large intestine. Okay fine.
They say it's the last section of the colon,
that's
what they say, the colon. What happens, the large intestine feeds the
colon and the colon to the rectum, is that how it works?
Okay fine. Okay, got it. Okay, fine, the rectum. All
right, okay. וכמה? Vechama? How big of a hole is not a
problem? אמר רבי אילא אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi
Yochanan מקום הדבק ברובו, mekom hadevek berubo, where the thighs stick together
even if it's cut the majority of it, שלא במקום הדבק shelo
bimekom hadevek or until the majority of it is probably more
correct, until the majority of it is cut or
removed it is okay. שלא במקום הדבק Shelo bimekom hadevek where the
thighs don't stick together, that's going to be במשהו, bemashehu, that will
be a problem of even a משהו. mashehu. So this whole big
קולא kula applies where the thighs are together and there even if
the majority of it is missing of this rectum it's okay. אמרו
רבנן קמיה דרבא משמיה דרב נחמן Amru rabanan kammai deRava mishmeih deRav
Nachman so they said this over in the name of רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, this position that even if the majority is missing where
they stick together but a משהו mashehu where it doesn't. אמר Amar
he said, לאו ניאמינא לכו lav niamina lechu have I not told
you, לא תיתלו ביה בוקי סריקי, lo titlu beih buki sariki,
don't sort of hang on רב נחמן Rav Nachman empty vessels, which
means don't say these bad ideas in the name of רב נחמן.
Rav Nachman. Again, interestingly, yet again, a question about the exact מסורה
mesorah and are we repeating, are we reporting things correctly. הכי אמר
רב נחמן, Hachi amar Rav Nachman, this is what רב נחמן Rav
Nachman says, not what you said, he said, this is what he
said, מקום הדבק אפילו ניטל כולו כשר, mekom hadevek afillu nital kulo
kasher, where the thighs are stick together even if the entire rectum
is missing it's כשר, kasher, which is pretty amazing, how is the
bowel movement going to get out of the animal, והוא שנשתייר בו
כדי תפיסה, vehu shenishtayer bo kedei tfisa,
as long as an amount that you can grab onto remains. וכמה?
Vechama? How big is that? אמר אביי Amar Abaye כמלא ביטדא בטורא,
kemalei bitda betura,
even as small as a finger in a large ox. If even
a finger's width... Of the rectum remains, it's still כשר. kosher. Again,
I have no idea what would actually happen to an animal that
that was the case and whether it would get out, you would
think it would be a טריפה, treifa, you'd think all of that
waste matter would get back into the system, I don't know. All
right, anyway, but he was very insistent that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
would say even the entire thing.
I think one of those like science versus הלכה halacha things.
You would think, but of course we're not, you know, we're not
doctors and we're not, so maybe who knows. All right. הכרס הפנימי.
Hakeres Hapnimi. The inner כרס. keres. Now what is the הלכה halacha
here? Very interesting, right? Because the משנה Mishnah said an inner and
outer כרס. keres. Right? The משנה Mishnah said that the inner כרס
keres is, I'll read it again, it says, הכרס הפנימי
שניקבה או שניקבה רוב החיצונה. hakeres hapnimi shenikva o shenikva rov hachitzona.
If a little bit of the inner one, if a hole in
the inner one is a טריפה, treifa, or the majority of the
outer one. Now what is the inner כרס, keres, which is the
outer כרס? keres? Now let me remind you actually, here by the
way is a nice picture, right? The כרס keres is the first
thing it goes into, it's this huge thing, and from the כרס
keres gets chopped up and then it goes into the מסס mesas
and the בית הכוסות, beis hakosos, gets regurgitated, whatever, and finally goes
into the קיבה. keiva. Okay, here it is in situ though and
you can see how huge it is, up get a picture here,
okay, this huge thing, 24, is the כרס. keres. Okay, so what
is and these parts of it, all of this is the כרס.
keres. So what is the inner כרס keres which is משהו mashehu
and what is the outer כרס? keres? So that is which is
רוב. rov. So that is the question. Okay, so it could be
some, so at one time, you know, there was one possibility that
the inner one was the one that was protected by the long,
by the long what do you call it ribs, you know, and
the, oh wait, that was the outer one, the inner one was
more into the cow, the inner one was where the short ribs
are. Okay, but anyway this is the question, what is the inner
what is the outer, the inner one is even a tiny hole,
the outer one is רובו. rubo. So let's take a look. So
where are we?
Okay, here we go. Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav, העיד נתן בר שילא ריש טבחיא דציפורי. He'id Natan
bar Shila reish tavchaya deTzipori. So נתן בר שילא Natan bar Shila
the head butcher of ציפורי Tzipori testified לפני רבי lifnei Rebbi in
the name of רבי, Rebbi, משום רבי נתן mishum Rebbi Natan in
the name of רבי נתן. Rebbi Natan. So apparently he had a
ruling from רבי נתן Rebbi Natan and he reported it to רבי.
Rebbi. איזהו היא הכרס הפנימי? Eizehu hi hakeres hapnimi? What is the
inner כרס keres where even a tiny hole? שניא דיבי. Sanya Divi.
What is hated by the foxes. Now that is a technical term,
okay, but that's what the words mean and that is assumed generally
to be this thing here 22. It's actually a completely separate organ,
oh no that's the טחול, tchol, that's the spleen, but it is
a separate organ, I just want to see if they have it
in this picture. Maybe they have it back in this picture.
Yeah, 21. So you see this thing, this is a totally separate
organ, you can't see the כרס keres it's behind all this fat,
okay, but this is this separate organ where actually waste matter goes.
So as it's sort of chewing it up, stuff that's not digestible
or whatever waste matter goes into this separate organ, I forgot what
it's called, but I don't know we don't have it in humans.
Anyway, well here they're calling it,
what do they call it?
This שניא דיבי Sanya Divi is a cecum.
Cecum, there you go, now we know. Anyway, it's called that because
the point is that even animals won't eat it because it's got
all this disgusting waste matter.
Okay,
so that's what it is, it's really not the same organ as
the כרס keres itself. So that's what they say it is. שניא
דיבי. Sanya Divi. וכן אמר רבי יהושע בן קרחה שניא
דיבי. Vechen amar Rebbi Yehoshua ben Karcha Sanya Divi. רבי ישמעאל אומר
אסטומכא דכרסא. Rebbi Yishmael omer istomcha dekarsa. The stomach of the כרס.
keres. אסטומכא. Istomcha. Okay, now stomach apparently in ancient texts meant the
opening. Okay, so again not exactly clear though which part that that
is actually that that is referring to, maybe it means the opening
where it opens into the other organs because the inner one is
more on the inside of it. Okay, so not exactly clear what
that refers to. The גמרא Gemara goes on, אסטומכא דכרסא. istomcha dekarsa.
רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן מקום צר יש בכרס ואיני יודע איזהו
הוא. Rav Assi amar Rebbi Yochanan mokom tzar yesh bakeres ve'eini yodeia
eizehu hu. There's a narrowing of the כרס keres and I don't
know exactly where it is and that's what's considered the inner כרס.
keres. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק נפל
כרסא בבירא. Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak nafal karsa bebeira. So your
כרס keres now fell into a well. Meaning it's wonderful to tell
us you know a הלכה, halacha, but if you don't know what
it describes what good does this do for us? Okay, there's an
expression in the גמרא Gemara נפלה פיתא בבירא, nafla pita bebeira, like
the bread fell in the well. So this seems to be a
play on that. Okay, the כרס keres fell in the well. What
good does that פסק psak do for us?
Right, so this is punctured and it's טריפה, treifa, right?
Yes, but only the inner כרס. keres. The outer one it has
to be the רוב. rov. So we're trying to figure out what
is the inner one. Okay. אמר רב אחא בר רב אביא אמר
רב אסי מן המיצר ולמטה. Amar Rav Acha bar Rav Avya amar
Rav Assi min hameitzar ulematah. So going talking about מקום צר, mokom
tzar, so where it narrows and below. So again that's not exactly
clear and certainly for me on this picture I don't see a
specific place where it narrows but okay. Somehow where it starts narrowing.
That's where it's considered to be the inner one. רבי יעקב בר
נחמני אמר שמואל מקום שאין בו מילת. Rebbi Yaakov bar Nachmani amar
Shmuel mokom she'ein bo milat. Now that's easier you can
even... so this fuzzy area starts is only at the beginning of
the כרס. keres. Afterwards it's smooth. So מילת milat is like felt.
They're describing it as felt. So basically the inner one is where
the felt-like starts stuff stops. So that's inner, the outer is, you
know, where the felt-like stuff is, which by the way somewhat corresponds
to the stuff directly under the full rib cage. They're not drawing
the ribs all the way here, but directly under the full rib
cage as opposed to behind them. Okay, so the inner one is
where that felt-like stuff stops.
מקום שאין בו מילת. makom she-ein bo milat. So the גמרא Gemara
says where were we?
ורבי
אבינא אמר גניבא משמיה דרב טפח בוושט סמוך לכרס זו היא כרס
הפנימית. Ve-Rabbi Avina amar Geniva mishmei de-Rav tefach baveshet somuch lakeres zu
hi keres hapenimit. No, there's like a handbreadth inside the כרס keres
right near the esophagus which is called the inner one, which is
strange because until now inner one has meant more towards the rear
of the animal and here he's saying that the inner one means
some place right near the esophagus. So אמי במערבא משמיה דרבי יוסי
בר חנינא, Ammi be-Ma'arava mishmei de-Rabbi Yose bar Chanina, so they said
in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, כל הכרס כולה זו היא כרס הפנימית,
kol hakeres kulo zo hi keres hapenimit, the entire כרס keres is
the inner כרס. keres. So
if that's true, ואיזו היא כרס החיצון? ve-eizu hi keres hachitzon? What's
the outer כרס keres where it does not where you need to
have the רוב? rov? בשר החופה את רוב הכרס. basar hachofeh et
rov hakeres. That is talking about the diaphragm, let's see what it
is. Anyway, there was some type of a muscle that runs underneath
the כרס, keres, I don't know if you can see it here,
which covers not it's like a muscle, maybe it's not diaphragm, but
it's some muscle that runs underneath the כרס keres and that is
and that is what is the outer כרס keres which really not
a muscle at all, it really it's really not a stomach at
all, it really means something that is outside of the כרס. keres.
Let me just see if they have the picture here.
171, 172.
In the in the book שיחת חולין Sichat Chullin they had a
very nice picture.
Oh, here we go, abdominal muscles, excuse me, not diaphragm, right, that's
with the lung. Abdominal muscles. So you see here, here you've got
the כרס. keres. Rivky, are you looking? We have a gorgeous picture
here. Okay, here here you've got the כרס keres and here you've
got these abdominal muscles and they run so that's considered the outer,
not outer meaning towards the outer, you know, towards the front of
the animal or inside the animal. Outside, it's much more מחמיר machmir
because it means any hole in the entire כרס keres is a
problem, but outer means the thing that is outside of the כרס
keres and is these abdominal muscles. So it's with these abdominal muscles,
the area that runs underneath the כרס, keres, that's why it's called
רוב הכרס rov hakeres because it doesn't go under the whole כרס,
keres, it only goes under the majority of the כרס, keres, but
it goes under other parts of the animal as well, but the
section of these abdominal muscles that go under the כרס, keres, that's
where a tear of רוב rov is a problem, but the כרס
keres itself any hole is a problem. So yes, that is a
very מחמיר machmir position.
Okay, רבה בר רב הונא אמר מפרטא, Rabba bar Rav Huna amar
mafrata, the where it is torn open. מאי מפרטא? mai mafrata? What
does it mean where it's torn open? אמר רב אביא היכא דפרו
אטבחא, amar Rav Avia heicha de-pro atvacha, where they where the butchers
tear it open. So you kill the animal, you hang it, you,
you know, you slice it down its stomach, you open it up,
so all that area that is exposed when the butchers open it,
that's considered the inner כרס keres and the stuff that's not exposed
is considered to be the outer כרס. keres. Okay, so which
by the way works well in the idea that the question is
that the outer one is the one that's under the full rib
cage because when you pour tear it open, right, the stuff that's
under the full rib cage presumably still stays there until you crack
open the ribs and the only stuff that really gets exposed immediately
is the stuff that's not under the full rib cage. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara will say like this. בנהרדעא עבדי כרבה בר
רב הונא. Be-Nahardea avdi ke-Rabba bar Rav Huna. In נהרדעא Nahardea they
went like רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar Rav Huna, which was
the stuff where it was exposed when it was torn open, that
was the inner one where a hole makes a difference. אמר ליה
רב אשי לאמימר, amar leh Rav Ashi le-Amemar, רב אשי Rav Ashi
said to אמימר Amemar who was from נהרדעא, Nahardea, כל הני שמעתתא
דמאי? kol hani shemateta de-mai? What about all the other positions? Which
is a weird question. What do you mean what about the other
positions? This is the way we פסקן, pasken, but maybe he understood
that since it was so debated it was funny that he was
just straight פסקןing paskening this way. אמר ליה כולהו שייכן בדרבה בר
רב הונא, amar leh kulhu shaychan be-de-Rabba bar Rav Huna, he said
to him they're all included in רבה בר רב הונא, Rabba bar
Rav Huna, meaning all these other descriptions which is where it gets
narrow, where there's none of this felt-type of thing, all of that
is, you know, when if is, you know, all of those areas,
meaning my the area we're saying which is exposed when you open
it up the animal, that right it's a superset, it's even bigger
than in terms of defining the inner כרס keres than these other
places. So actually our position is the more מחמיר machmir one. We're
saying the entire area that's exposed which includes all those other definitions
of the inner stomach, of the inner
כרס. keres. So so ודרב אסי... ve-de-Rav Assi... רב אחבא בר אבא
Rav Achba bar Abba already explained it's where the כרס keress starts
to narrow, which presumably is also in the part that gets exposed.
ודרבי אבינא ודבני מערבא מאי, ud'Rabbi Avina u'd'bnei Ma'arava mai, what about
these other two positions? רבי אבינא Rabbi Avina says that it's right
near the esophagus, which is completely not what you're saying. And how
about the position that it's the entire כרס keress is the inner
כרס keress and it's only the abdominal muscles that are more lenient?
אמר ליה הני ודאי פליגי. amar lei hani vaddi pligi. All right,
you're right. Those obviously disagree with our ruling. So we're not ruling
like everybody. Okay, so this is a question, you know, a lot
of different positions. The outer כרס keress is a much bigger leniency.
Does the outer כרס keress mean the stuff closer to the front
of the animal? Then a question exactly where you'd draw the line,
where it's salty, under the rib cage, etc. etc. Or does the
outer thing mean these muscles that are on the outside and the
entire כרס keress even a hole makes a difference? So the גמרא,
Gemara, you know, has a lot of different opinions as to what,
but at least in נהרדעא Nehardea they took, you know, they didn't
rule all of the חומרות, chumras, but they ruled like a lot
of the positions by saying the part that's exposed when you open
it up. Okay, so now yes.
I
have a question about this stuff from רב אשי Rav Ashi was
late.
That means that they really didn't have a standard practice of כשרות
kashrut the whole time. The whole... Right. I mean, a lot of
the fact that the גמרא Gemara says at the end הלכתא, hilchata,
and that הלכתא hilchata was very, very late, which meant until the
גמרא Gemara and a very, very... but whatever. Yeah. But, you know,
until the גמרא Gemara ruled that way, yeah, there was a lot
of variation. It's true now, you know, you don't know how frequently
טריפות treifas occurred. Right. I mean, look, in the משנה Mishnah you
have that in the place of רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili,
it was רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, they would eat עוף
בחלב, of b'chalav, you know, which is pretty radical, which means as
a regular practice. טריפות treifas here are only something if it happens
to come up. But yeah, the idea that there was a wide
variety of practice, you know, in many different areas, you know, is
true.
But we're now striving for one standard.
Well, that's an interesting question.
You know, you're probably not happy with, right, right, right, sometimes they
don't have any problem with that, sometimes they're trying to say what's
the הלכתא, hilchata, what's the הלכה, halacha, what's the הלכה, halacha, you
know, and they're going around and trying to find what the מסורה
mesorah is, and it ends up saying
הלכתא hilchata etc.
right, exactly. So it's a little bit unclear, but you are right,
they definitely seemed tolerant of a variety of practice. Absolutely. All right,
let's just try to reach to the bottom of the page here,
get down one more section. רבי יהודה אומר בגדולה. Rabbi Yehuda omer
bigdola. Now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said if it is a large
animal, this idea that you need רוב rov of the outer כרס,
keress, whatever the outer כרס keress is, but but it is something
you need רוב. rov. So he said רוב rov by a large
animal, a טפח tefach by a small animal. So or no, did
he say the opposite? He said רוב, rov, I'm sorry, רוב rov
by a small animal, a טפח tefach by a large animal. So
what's small and big? So אמר רב בנימין בר יפת אמר רבי
אלעזר, amar Rav Binyamin bar Yephet amar Rabbi Elazar, לא גדולה גדולה
ממש, lo gdola gdola mamash, big doesn't really mean huge, ולא קטנה
קטנה ממש, velo ktana ktana mamash, and small doesn't mean
tiny, אלא כל שניקרה בטפח ולא הוי רובה זו היא ששנינו בגדולה
טפח. ela kol shenikra b'tefach velo havei ruba zu hi sheshoninu bigdola
tefach. If you can have a tear of a טפח tefach and
it's not yet the majority, so that suffices to make it a
טריפה. treifa. So that what it means a big one, where a
טפח tefach is still not a majority, then even a טפח tefach
makes it a
טריפה. treifa. וזה ששנינו בטפח רובה ולא הוי טפח, v'zeh sheshoninu b'tefach
ruba velo havei tefach, let's say you tore the majority of this
outer כרס keress and it is still not a טפח, tefach, so
that's a pretty small כרס keress if you can tear the majority
and it not be a טפח. tefach. זו היא ששנינו בקטנה ברוב.
zu hi sheshoninu b'ktana b'rov. That's what means a small one
where you tear the majority before you tear the טפח, tefach, a
small one even then it goes by רוב, rov, which basically means
the way we would say it is, whichever... a רוב rov or
טפח tefach whichever comes first. The smaller of a רוב rov or
טפח. tefach. So with a large animal the smaller of the two
will be a טפח, tefach, with a small animal the smaller of
the two will be the רוב. rov. Okay, so that's what he
says, it's a רוב rov or טפח tefach whichever comes first. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says, רובה ולא הוי טפח פשיטא. ruba
velo havei tefach peshita. If it's a majority and not a טפח,
tefach, that's obvious. Majority of something is always a problem. Now who
knows, you know, maybe even but okay, once you're admitting that a
tear is a problem, seems to be the point. Some places tears
aren't a problem, but once you're admitting a tear isn't a problem,
of course a majority is an issue. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא צריכא דהוי טפח במשהו. lo tzricha dehavei tefach b'mashehu. We're not,
no,
it's a case where it is a majority, but a tiny bit
more will get you to a טפח. tefach. This is the way
רש"י Rashi reads it.
מהו דתימא אימא עד דמיקרי בטפח לא הוי טריפה, ma d'teima eima
ad d'mikra b'tefach lo havei treifa, maybe we would still insist on
our טפח tefach standard. We would say, okay, it's 51 percent, but
maybe you know what, one more percent will get you a טפח,
tefach, you need to get to be a טפח tefach before it's
a טריפה. treifa. קמשמע לן kamashmalan that no, you go by רוב.
rov. And תוספות Tosafot says what type of crazy הוה אמינא havah
aminah is that? If we assume majority always matters, how could I
have said, oh, but maybe I'll demand a little bit more until
you get a טפח. tefach. תוספות Tosafot has... another way of reading
this גמרא Gemara but anyway we'll just stick with it for this.
אמר גניבא אמר רב אסי, Amar Gneva amar Rav Assi, so גניבא
Gneva one wonders who would have named their kid גניבא Gneva anyway,
said in the name of רב אסי, Rav Assi, נקטרה כסלע טריפה.
niktra k'sela treifa. If it has a hole the size of a
סלע sela it's a טריפה, treifa, this outer כרס keres whatever it
is. So now what does it mean the size of a סלע?
sela?
What does נקטרה niktra mean?
Like a window was made. You made a little, so you cut
a little a little hole in it like a little window-like hole,
you know, it's not like a point hole, you cut a little,
you know, a little peephole, whatever, window into it. So שאם תמתח
תעמוד על טפח, she'im timatach taamod al tefakh, why? Because a circle
the size of a סלע, sela, remember when it has to tear
a טפח, tefakh, it's not a טפח tefakh by a טפח, tefakh,
it just means a straight line by a טפח. tefakh. So if
you made a circle the size of a סלע, sela, the circumference
of that circle is a טפח. tefakh. And therefore it counts as
a טפח tefakh tear. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא לדידי בפרשה לי
מיניה דגניבא אמעברא
דנהרדעא, Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba l'didi b'farsha li minei d'Gneva amabra
deNahardea, it was explained to me in the name of גניבא Gneva
by the bridge of נהרדעא, Nahardea, anyway somebody we were having a
discussion with somebody else and he explained to me the explanation of
a מימרא's memra statement: כסלע כשרה, k'sela kesheira, it's exactly the size
of a סלע sela it's כשרה, kesheira, יתר מכסלע טריפה, yeter mik'sela
treifa, a little bit bigger,
טריפה. treifa. וכמה יתר מכסלע? V'kama yeter mik'sela? How much is a
little bit bigger? So אמר רב יוסף כגון דעייל תלת קשיותא בציפא
בדוחקא, Amar Rav Yosef kegon d'ayel tlat kashyata betzipa bedocheka, like three
date nuts, date pits, whatever, can go through it with their little
meat of the date on it, so would go you could fit
through the hole tightly. בלא ציפא, B'lo tzipa, then that's good or
bad? Then that's bad. That's big enough to be bad. בלא ציפא,
B'lo tzipa, without the little meat of the date on it, you
take three date nuts, date pits and put them through, בריוח, b'revach,
they can go easily through, then that hole is big enough to
be a problem that it's equivalent to a tear of a טפח.
tefakh. And that we will stop.